把头抬起来
Lift up your head.
他已经没有乳牙了
He has no more baby teeth.
我估计他12岁了  甚至13岁了
I'd estimate he's 12, even 13.
米歇尔·菲力宾
Michelle, Filipina?
米歇尔
Michelle ?
您姓什么
What is your surname?
姓什么
Surname?
-赛达德  -赛达德
- Sedad. - Sedad.
你有护照吗  入境签证呢
Do you have a passport? Entry visa?
在家里  跟我的老板在一起
At the house, with my employer.
莱玛·贝克罗
Lama Bekoum.
谁是莱玛啊
Who is Lama ?
-莱玛  你怀孕了吗  -是的
- Lama, you are pregnant? - Yes.
怀了多久了
How far along?
七个月了
Seven months.
好的  明爱会会见你的
OK, Caritas will see you.
谁是泰吉斯·埃罗
Who is Tigest Ailo ?
埃塞俄比亚的泰吉斯·埃罗
The Ethiopian, Tigest Ailo ?
你是泰吉斯吗
You're Tigest ?
何以为家
法院开庭了
Court is in session.
赞恩·哈吉
Zain Al Hajj.
取下手铐  走向长凳
Remove the handcuffs. Approach the bench.
苏阿德和塞利姆·哈吉
Souad and Selim Al Hajj.
是的
Yes.
原告被拘留了
The plaintiff is in detention.
他现在没有手铐  让我看看你的手
He is present without handcuffs. Show me your hands.
另外他出席的律师娜丁·阿朗
Also in attendance... His lawyer Nadine Al Aalam.
被告也在场
The accused are also present
塞利姆和苏阿德·哈吉
Selim and Souad Al Hajj,
由他们的律师赛依德·塔梅尔代表
represented by their lawyer Saiid Tamer.
你知道自己为什么在这吗  苏阿德
Do you know why you're here, Souad ?
是的  我知道  法官大人
Yes, I know, Your Honor.
为什么
Why?
我知道我的儿子正在监狱里服刑
I know my son is serving time in prison,
但是我不知道为什么我们又被拖进来
but I don't know why he dragged us here again.
我们谁都不是  有人摆布我们
We're nobodies, anybody pushes us around!
你是在赞恩的审判中被传唤的目击者  对吗
You were called as witnesses in Zain's trial, correct?
是的
Yes.
而且你作证了是吗
And you testified?
是的
Yes.
而现在你是被告
And now you stand accused.
你知道为什么赞恩被判有罪吗
You know why Zain was found guilty?
赞恩因为一些小事情惹了麻烦
Zain got into trouble for some kidstuff.
-小事情吗  -他被判了五年的刑
Kidstuff? He was sentenced to 5 years!
小事情吗
Kidstuff?
所以
So...
你多大了  赞恩
How old are you Zain ?
我不知道  你问他们
I don't know, ask them.
法官大人  赞恩在出生时没被登记
Your Honor, Zain was not registered at birth,
也从未在国家登记过
and never registered with the State.
虽然他的父母不知道
Since his parents clearly don't know
他准确的出生日期
his exact date of birth...
但这里是医生的报告
Here is the doctor's report
证明事情发生时赞恩在12岁左右
attesting Zain was around 12 at the time of the incident.
所以他12岁左右吗
So he's around 12 years old?
的确如此
Precisely.
赞恩  你住在哪
Where do you live Zain ?
鲁米耶未成年监狱
Roumieh Prison for Minors.
你在6月15日被捕  此后一直服刑
You were arrested June 15th and have been serving time since,
你知道为什么吗
do you know why?
因为我用刀捅了个狗东西
Because I stuck a knife into the son of a dog.
你捅了个人吗
You stabbed someone?
对  一个狗东西
Yes, a son of a dog.
真的吗
Really?
你确定吗
You insist?
法庭禁止喧哗
No laughing in court!
你都惹了什么麻烦
What's all this trouble you caused?
上电视  上报纸  还从监狱里打电话出去
On T.V., in the papers. Your phone call from prison...
-你知道你为什么在这里吗  -知道
- Do you know why you're here? - Yes.
为什么
Why?
我想指控我的父母
I want to accuse my parents.
你为什么想指控你的父母
Why do you want to accuse your parents?
因为他们把我带到了这个世界
For bringing me into the world.
早上好
Good day.
我想要两盒曲马多
I'd like 2 boxes of Tramadol.
曲马多是一种镇痛药  长期服用易成瘾  多被当作廉价毒品进行交易
你需要有处方
You need a prescription.
-这是给谁买的  -我妈妈
- Who's it for? - My mother.
她为什么不能来
Why can't she come?
她的胃做了手术
She had a stomach operation.
她的背摔坏了
She broke her back.
-她的医生开了这个处方吗  -是的
- Her doctor prescribed this? - Yes.
你父亲为什么不能来
Why can't your father come?
他瘫痪了
He's paralyzed.
-夫人  你来这里看望谁  -我儿子
- Who are you here to see, madam? - My son.
-他叫什么名字  -易卜拉欣·哈吉
- His name? - Ibrahim Al Hajj.
-易卜拉欣·哈吉吗  -对
- Ibrahim Al Hajj? - Yes.
-苏阿德阿姨  -在这
- Aunt Souad? - Up here!
马苏德  是你吗  你怎么样
Massoud? Is that you? How are you?
你怎么样  我亲爱的
How are you, my dear?
我的儿子易卜拉欣跟你在一起吗
Is my son Ibrahim with you?
没有  他们把他带到另一个牢房了
No, they took him to another cell.
她在叫你呢
She's calling to you!
跟他说再见
Tell him goodbye.
跟你的表哥说再见
Say goodbye to your cousin.
你的兄弟们都跟你在一个牢房吗
Are all your brothers in your cell?
对  都在
Yes, everyone.
愿上帝保佑你
May God protect you.
我们把价格提到15美金一口
We raised prices to $15 a gulp.
我们的手都被泡烂了  拧拧就出水
Our hands are all messed up from the soaking and wringing.
我们的“袜子果汁”要花费两磅多肉的价钱呢
Our "sock juice" costs more than 2 pounds of meat!
我为你骄傲
I'm proud of you!
快点
Hurry up!
-我们明天有考试吗  -自己看课表
- Do we have a test tomorrow? - Look at your schedule.
这是给你妈妈的
This is for your mother.
这是给可爱的萨哈尔的
And this is for my lovely Sahar.
我想她
I miss her.
甘草和拉面
Licorice and ramen.
谢谢你
Thank you.
再见
Later.
阿萨德的爸爸是个笨蛋
Assaad's father is a bonehead.
当他往水箱里灌水的时候
When he fills the water tank,
我们都被他破水管弄湿了
we get soaked because of his crappy plumbing!
那个傻子把这个当礼物吗  就这个耗子窝
That fool thinks this is a gift? This rathole?
萨哈尔
Sahar!
这算不上房子
This isn't a house!
就是个猪圈
It's a shelter for pigs!
出去  你会把自己电死的  该死
Get out! You'll electrocute yourself, damn it!
这破地方  还不如住路边上
The awful place! Go live in the street.
那地方还大呢
There's plenty of room!
赞恩  这些菜怎么都烂了
Zain, why are these vegetables rotten?
你又把阿萨德弄哭了吗
Did you upset Assaad?
赞恩  他没给你甘草和拉面吗
Zain, did he give you licorice and ramen?
天还没亮呢  别叫我
It's not daybreak yet! Get off my case!
快起床吧懒东西
Get up, good-for-nothing!
这个果汁是最好的  别再喝别家的啦
This juice is best, forget the rest!
萨哈尔  跟我过来
Sahar, come here with me.
你的短裤上为什么有血
Why is there blood on your shorts?
血在哪
Blood where?
快点  趁没人看见
Hurry before someone sees us.
还记得你的朋友阿丽亚怎么了吗
Remember what happened to your friend Alia?
当她妈妈发现他们把她锁在家里时
When her mother found out they locked her up at home,
那只大猪过来抓她
then that big swine came to take her.
妈妈会不想要你的  她会把你扔在街上
Mom won't want you. She'll toss you in the street.
-她会把你给阿萨德  -但是阿萨德人很好
- She'll give you to Assaad. - But Assaad is really nice.
他是个混蛋
He's an asshole!
他给我甘草和拉面
He gives me licorice and ramen.
他给你吃下脚料
He'll feed you scraps!
他们会把你给阿萨德  他们会不要你
They'll give you to Assaad, they'll get rid of you.
我们就再也见不到你了
We'll never see you again.
他会把你跟老鼠放在一起
He'll put you with the rats,
把你锁起来  把窗户遮住
lock you up, cover the windows...
永远不让你出去
Never let you outside.
他会每三天给你一点水和过期的拉面
He'll give you a drop of water every 3 days with expired ramen.
你没看见他的耳朵吗  下水道里的一只老鼠咬了他
Didn't you see his ear? A sewer rat bit him.
给  把它穿上
Here, put this on.
你好了吗
Are you finished?
好了
Yes.
给
Here.
我要用它做什么
What do I do with it?
把它像这样放在你的大腿间
Put it like this between your legs.
你的头发真好看  谁给你梳的
Your hair is so lovely! Who styled it?
给我看看
Show me.
哟  小老板  你活干完了吗
So chief, are you finished?
我得把更多罐头收起来
I have to put more cans away,
但是我妈妈需要萨哈尔
but my mother needs Sahar.
你们俩都留下来  我喜欢你妹妹在这
Stay, both of you. I enjoy having your sister here.
我晚点再把她带过来
I'll bring her back later.
我会跟你妈妈说的
I'll talk to your mother.
再见
Goodbye.
小心点  别把那些破布乱扔
Careful, don't leave those rags just anywhere.
我教你把它们藏在哪
I'll show you where to hide them.
-你明白吗  -明白
- You understand? - Yes.
不要把它们扔在垃圾里
Don't toss them in the garbage.
比蜜甜的甜菜汁
Juice of beet, flavor so sweet!
比血红的红番茄
Tomato so red, use your head!
250块
It's 250.
谢谢你  再见
Thank you, bye.
给
Here.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
拿两个
Take two of them.
你想要什么
What do you want?
-就想给你看个东西  -走开
- Just to show you something. - Leave me alone.
就一小会
Just a little while!
去你的  你个猪头
Screw yourself, you pig.
别管他  赞恩
Leave him, Zain.
别惹我
Don't piss me off!
为什么要去上学
Why sign up for school?
不可能的  别想了  继续跟着阿萨德工作吧
Out of the question. Forget it, just keep working for Assaad.
别把事情越搞越糟了
Why complicate things?
他就不能去学着认几个字吗
Couldn't he go learn a few words?
去你妹妹身边  但别吵醒她
Go beside your sister, but don't wake her.
让他去上学
Let him go to school.
他们为孩子提供食物和衣服
They give for food and clothing, for the children...
我们怎么跟阿萨德说
What do we tell Assaad?
我会跟他讲的
I'll talk to him.
我会早上去学校
I'll go to school in the morning,
下午帮他干活的
and work for him in the afternoon.
扎赫拉  瞧瞧人家邻居的儿子法里德
Look Farid, the neighbor's son, Zahra.
从学校带着各种各样的东西回来
Returns from school with all kinds of things
他们给我们床垫  衣服
They give us mattresses, clothing...
安静
Be quiet!
至少他会在那里吃饭
At least he'll eat there,
然后给他的妹妹带吃的回来
and bring back food for his sisters.
他们有酒店的剩菜  都是筵席上的大菜
They get hotel leftovers, fancy wedding food.
我们不如好好利用  你为什么这么顽固
Let's take advantage! Why are you so stubborn?
我们周一看《求主垂怜》
Inch'Allah we'll see Monday.
《求主垂怜》是2013年一部法国拍摄的剧情片  讲述了一位年轻的加拿大女医生到巴以边境当战地医生的故事
《求主垂怜》
Inch'Allah ?
你想让我对着这片面包发誓吗
You want me to swear on this bread?
我说了是的
I said yes.
如果阿萨德生气了把我们赶出去了呢
And if Assaad gets angry and kicks us out?
别担心  他不会的
Don't worry, he won't.
我们会在放学之后把赞恩送去  让他加班
We'll send Zain after school, and he'll take overtime.
我蛋蛋上的肥皂
Soap from my balls!
你干嘛撅着嘴
Why are you pouting?
放轻松
Take it easy.
带个气罐给街上的恩哈比
Bring a gas canister to Em Habib down the street.
巴伊亚夫人  我做完了
Madam Bahia, I'm done.
-这个多少钱  -13000
- How much is it? - 13000.
别碰我  混蛋
Don't touch me, asshole!
这些母鸡哪来的
Where do these hens come from?
谁买的
Who brought them?
阿萨德  他在楼上
Assaad. He's upstairs.
阿萨德在这吗
Assaad is here?
是的
Yes.
妈妈
Mom?
阿萨德和他爸爸在这干什么呢
What are Assaad and his father doing here?
别捣乱  你会看到的
Don't make a scene. You'll see.
-他们为什么在这  -冷静
- Why are they here? - Calm down.
他们在和你爸爸讨论租金的问题
They're talking rent with your father.
我得砍掉我的胳膊
I'd cut off my left hand
然后他们给萨哈尔几只母鸡
and they give a few hens for Sahar.
等等  听我说
Wait, listen to me...
告诉那个贱人他在这不受欢迎
Tell that son of a bitch he's not welcome here
-你不明白吗  -去告诉他  要不然我去
- You don't understand? - Tell him or I will.
小声点
Lower your voice.
我对你的姐妹们发誓  我对上帝发誓
I swear by your sisters, I swear to God.
什么事都没有
There's none of that going on.
那为什么萨哈尔化着妆呢
So why is Sahar wearing makeup?
她那是在模仿我为了好玩
She's imitating me for fun.
他们一喝完果汁  我就把他们赶走
As soon as they finish their juice, I'm kicking them out.
听着  别这样
Listen, don't.
去告诉他们这事行不通
Go tell him it won't work.
你跟他们说  要不然我去
Tell him or I will.
我不想听
I don't want to hear it.
你想让他把我们扔到大街上吗
You want him to throw us in the street?
一个字也别说
Not a word.
欢迎  亲爱的邻居
Welcome dear neighbors!
阿布·阿萨德  请自便
Abou Assaad, please help yourself.
谢谢
Thank you.
来一点  阿萨德
Have some, Assaad.
迪尔  带你妹妹去另一间房间
Dearie, take your sister into the other room.
把那丑陋的口红擦掉
Wipe off that ugly lipstick.
你穿着那条裙子像个巫婆
You look like a witch in that dress.
萨哈尔
Sahar...
Sahar!
醒醒  我想带你去个地方
Wake up, I want to bring you somewhere.
-哪里  -我待会再告诉你  醒醒
- Where? - I'll tell you later. Wake up.
在我回来时准备好
Be ready when I get back.
别告诉任何人
Don't tell anyone.
去科拉多少钱
How much to Kola?
一千块
1000.
我和妹妹两个人一千块钱够吗  她坐在我的腿上
Is 1000 enough with my sister, sitting on my lap?
你妹妹在哪
Where's your sister?
在家里  我回去把她接来
At home, I'll go get her.
没问题  去接她吧
No problem, go get her.
我不想走  求你
I don't want to leave, mercy...
求你了  我不想走
Please! I don't want to go.
妈妈  我不想走
Mom, I don't want to go!
不许回来
Don't you dare come back here.
你要带她去哪里  一群白痴
Where are you taking her, you bunch of cretins?
去做那个贱人的女佣吗
To be a maid for that son of a bitch?
我想跟我哥哥呆在一起
I want to stay with my brother.
这不关你的事
It's none of your business.
-妈妈  她还只是个孩子  -管好你自己
- Mom, she's just a child. - Mind your own business.
我说了去一边去
Step away I said!
别在这添乱
Don't get mixed up in this.
你  下楼去
You, go downstairs.
赞恩  你敢动我就宰了你
Zain, try anything and I'll kill you.
我看出你的把戏了  你个混球
I see your game, you dirtball.
你还打算糊弄我们  你这个混账
You were going to screw us over, you piece of garbage.
你这等于是在让她去擦猪屎
You're sending her to wipe up that pig's filth!
去死吧你  到楼下去
Go screw yourself, you, get downstairs.
下去  现在
Down, now.
让她走
Let her go!
她不会去阿萨德那里
She won't go to Assaad!
小杂种
Little bastard!
把门开开  你个白痴
Open the door, you idiot.
我不想走  妈妈
I don't want to go, mom!
我不想走
I don't want to!
让我走
Let me go!
求你了妈妈  我不想走
Please mom, I don't want to go.
来  萨哈尔
Come, Sahar!
够了
That's enough!
你留在这  我说了
You stay here, I said!
-我想留下  求你了  -下楼
- I want to stay. Please! - Downstairs.
下楼  下楼
Downstairs! Downstairs!
妈妈仁慈点  求你了
Mom have mercy, please!
贱人
Son of a bitch.
够了  我受够了
Enough! I've had it with this hell!
妈妈  我不想走
Mom, I don't want to go!
够了  我真他妈受够了
Stop it! I've had enough of your whining!
让她上来
Make her climb on!
再说一个字  我就把你的舌头割掉
One more word and I cut your tongue off!
不
No!
萨哈尔
Sahar!
让他走
Let her go!
你现在开心了
Are you happy now?
学会装男人了
You're playing the big man?
你会后悔的  你真不是个东西
You'll be sorry, you good-for-nothing!
这是为了不让她受苦
It was to lift her out of misery.
和我们在一起她没有希望的
With me she was doomed.
她几乎没有地方睡觉
She barely has a bed to sleep in,
几乎吃不上饭  也不洗澡
barely any food or drink. She doesn't wash herself.
看不了电视
Never watches TV.
我告诉自己  把她嫁出去  至少她会有一张床
I told myself, "Marry her, at least she'll sleep in a bed."
一张真正的床
A real bed.
还有毯子
With a blanket.
她想吃多少就吃多少
She can eat as much as she likes.
-你没想到会导致这种情况吗  -从没想到
- You didn't know it would come to this? - Never!
我没有想要发生这种事
I didn't ask for this!
你觉得我会因为自己儿子捅了人而骄傲吗
You think I'm proud that my son stabbed someone?
有没有想过也许这一切并不是我们的错
Have you considered it might not be our fault?
我就是这样被养大的  我有什么错
I was born this way, raised this way, how have I done wrong?
我要是有得选  我会比你们所有人都好
If I'd had choices, I might be better than all of you!
你不能这样说  请你
You can't say such things. Please...
我走在街上都会被唾沫淹死
People spit on me in the street.
没人把我当人看
They treat me like an animal.
但我也没得选
I never asked for any of this.
他们说要是没有孩子  你就算不上男人
They told me, "You're not a man if you have no children."
孩子会是你的支柱
"Children will be your backbone."
backbone原意为脊柱
但为了他们我搞伤了背  还被伤透了心
But they broke my back, then broke my heart.
我当年就不该结婚
I curse the day I got married.
就不会有这么多的痛苦和麻烦
How did I sink to this misery?
我不是他  小鬼
I'm not him, kiddo.
只是长得像而已
We just look alike, that's all.
那里应该是蜘蛛  不是蟑螂
That should be a spider, not a cockroach.
不是吗
Isn't that right?
我不需要蜘蛛  我是蟑螂侠
I don't need a spider, I'm Cockroachman.
我要蜘蛛做什么
Why would I want a spider?
没错  我是蟑螂侠
That's right. I'm Cockroachman.
那你和蜘蛛侠有什么关系
How are you connected to Spiderman?
我们的关系啊
What's the relation?
我是他表哥
I'm his cousin.
那你们是表兄弟
So you're cousins?
没错  我是他的表哥
That's right. His cousin.
-你叫什么名字  -赞恩
What's your name? Zain.
-侯赛因吗  -是赞恩
- Hussein? - Zain!
赞恩
Zain!
你去哪里  赞恩
Where are you headed, Zain ?
去奶奶家
To my grandmother's.
-大声点  -去奶奶家
- Speak louder. - To my grandmother's!
去奶奶家吗
Your grandmother's?
她有你很幸运
Well, she's lucky to have you.
没人真的关心我
Nobody takes care of me.
-我的生活是  -拜托  先生  你的烟
- My life is... - Please, the cigarette.
拜托
Please.
停车  司机
Stop the bus, driver.
我想在这里下车
I'll get off here, if you please.
司机  等等
Driver, wait.
我也想在这里下车
I'd like to get off too, please.
吃了我的玉米棒  包你一生不后悔
Try my corn, you'll be glad you were born...
蟑螂侠先生
Mister Cockroachman?
老板在这儿吗
Is the owner here?
抱歉  什么
Excuse me?
老板在这儿吗
Is the owner here?
你找他干什么
What do you want with him?
我想要份工作
I'm looking for work.
什么样的工作
What kind of work?
什么都行  真的  我就要份工作
Anything, working is what counts.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
赞恩
Zain.
Zain?
你呢
And yours?
我叫泰吉斯
My name is Tigest.
我能拖地  我能洗碗
I can wash floors or clean dishes, for example.
我觉得不行
I don't think so.
我能给你打工吗
Do you need a worker?
你需要人帮你拿鱼竿吗
Need someone to carry your fishing rod?
你父母在哪
Where are your parents?
你的父母呢
Where are they?
先生  有250块果汁吗
Sir, do you have juice for 250?
或任何250块的东西吗
Or anything else for 250?
果汁要1000元
The juice is 1000.
-有便宜点的吗  -没有
- Anything less expensive? - No.
拿着吧
Go ahead.
拿着  我说了
Take it, I said.
没事儿  拿着吧
Don't worry, just take it.
这里有人了  女士
It's occupied, Madam.
这也是吗
Here too?
是的  这间坏了
Yes, and this one's out of service.
泰吉斯
Tigest?
你有吃吗
Do you have anything to eat?
拜托
Please.
赞恩
Zain.
奶在这里
The milk is over here, OK ?
11点喂他第一瓶  2点喂他另一瓶
Give him one at 11 o'clock, and another at 2.
我3点回来
I get back at 3 o'clock.
别出门  好吗
Don't leave the house, alright?
别让约纳斯哭  邻居会嫌烦
Don't let Yonas cry, the neighbour gets upset.
和你的朋友在一起  我会回来的  尤尼
Stay with your friend. I'll be back, Yoni.
这是你的新朋友  好吗
He's your new friend, OK?
赞恩是你的新朋友
Zain is your new friend.
你困了吗
Are you sleepy?
告诉他你没那么多钱
Tell him you have no money.
我说了  但他说不够一千五不给办证
I did, but he won't make my papers for less than $1500.
我必须重新办证了  都快过期了
I must renew them, they'll expire soon.
去吧  但尽快
Do what you can, but hurry.
好多人都被抓了
Plenty are getting arrested.
有时就在半夜抓你
Sometimes in the middle of the night.
你闻起来像狗屎  你个屎娃
You smell like shit, little shitter!
别动
Hold still!
坐下
Sit down.
坐下  见鬼
Sit down, damn it!
掉下来了
It fell over!
睡觉啦  睡觉啦
Go to sleep, go to sleep...
来吧  睡吧
Come on, go to sleep.
你要在这找什么
What do you want from here?
睡觉啦  小弟弟约纳斯
Go to sleep, little brother Yonas...
睡吧  别尿尿
Sleep, don't make a peep...
吃点玉米吧  亲爱的
Try some corn, my darling.
再见  哈鲁特
Bye, Harout.
来吧  来吧  欢迎光临
Come in, come in! Welcome!
非常火爆
Hot, hot!
吹  吹灭它们
Blow, blow it out.
吹吧  赞恩
Blow, Zain.
你多大了  赞恩
How old are you, Zain?
我不知道  可能12岁吧
I don't know. 12, I think.
你有兄弟姐妹吗
You have brothers and sisters?
很多
Many.
-你不想他们吗  -当然想
- You don't miss them? - Sure.
我最想我姐姐萨哈尔
The one I miss the most, is my sister Sahar.
-你姐姐在哪呢  -和她丈夫在一起
- Where is she? - With her husband.
她结婚了
She's married?
是的  当时还有乐队敲锣打鼓
Yes, there were drums and a darbouka.
我们在街上游行
We paraded in the street.
人们扔花和大米
People threw rice and flowers.
说着恭喜啊
Congratulations.
拉希尔·伊蕾莎
Rahil Eresa.
-姓呢  -希费劳
- Family name? - Shifara.
你知道为什么被拘留吗
Do you know why you're in prison?
为什么戴着手铐
Why you're handcuffed?
因为我没有工作证  没有身份证
I don't have residency permits. No papers.
你在哪里工作
Where did you work?
我为一位女士工作了六年
I worked for a lady for 6 years.
然后你走了对吗
Then you ran away?
她对你不好吗
The lady wasn't nice to you?
她打你吗
She beat you?
不  她对我很好  但我爱上了一个人
No, she was very nice, but I fell in love,
我怀孕了  所以就离开了
then I got pregnant and I left...
你什么了
You got what?
我怀孕了  然后就走了
I got pregnant and left...
你阿拉伯语说的很好
You speak Arabic well.
你听得懂我在说什么吗
You understand what I'm saying?
-是的  听得懂  -所以不用翻译吗
- Yes, I understand. - So no need for a translator?
不用
No.
你离开是不想让那位女士发现吗
So you left so the lady wouldn't find out?
我怕警察会把我孩子带走  然后把我驱逐出境
I was scared of police, they'd take my son and expel me.
我太害怕了  我不敢跟任何人说
I was scared so I didn't tell anyone.
所以你把约纳斯留给赞恩带吗
So you'd leave Yonas with Zain?
你回家的时候  他有好好照顾约纳斯吗
When you came home, he had taken good care of him?
你从没想过赞恩会伤害他吗
You never imagined he could hurt him?
头两天挺好的
Maybe the first 2 days,
之后我就开始相信他了
but afterwards, I started to trust him.
你想过赞恩会做出这事吗
Did you expect Zain to do what he did?
从没想到
Never.
他们就像兄弟
They were like brothers.
我没有怪赞恩
I never blamed Zain,
因为我很清楚阿斯普罗
because I know Aspro.
阿斯普罗是谁
Who is Aspro?
那个帮我伪造许可证的人
The guy who forged my permit.
我给你的期限到今天  不是吗
I gave you until today, no?
但我和我朋友说了
But I spoke to my friend.
她说她的证只要九百块
Her papers get made for $900.
那你找她去帮你办吧
Get her to make your papers then!
不  但为什么价格差这么多
No, but why is the price different?
别说瞎话了  别想骗我
Stop this nonsense, don't try to con me.
冷静下来  听我说
Calm down and let me talk.
我这是在帮你
I'm trying to help you here.
谁帮你取了泰吉斯这个名字  是我
Who gave you the name Tigest? I did.
去找你那个能900美元做许可证的朋友吧
Go to your friend who gets papers for $900.
别来烦我
Don't antagonize me.
求你了  我真的没有1500美元
Please, I couldn't get $1500.
看看这个  看起来假吗
Look at this! Does this look fake?
有了这个  没人会来骚扰你
Nobody will harass you with these papers.
证上的女人  嘣
The woman on these papers... Boom!
她被炸成了碎片
She blew up into small pieces.
她没什么亲戚朋友  都没有人来认尸
She had no one, no family. No one claimed her remains.
你不用再点那个美人痣了  不需要了
You can take off your beauty mark, no need for it.
好吧  但我还需要时间
OK, but I need more time.
亲爱的  我说你能省下1500美元
Darling, I said you can save $1500.
把约纳斯给我  许可证我送你
Give me Yonas and the permit will be free.
不要再跟我提约纳斯
Don't speak the name Yonas again,
我绝不答应
I'd never do that!
你孩子像个难民一样生活在这个国家
Your kid lives like a fugitive in this country.
哪天你的孩子被发现  你俩都要被驱逐出境
The day they discover him, you'll both be expelled.
他像老鼠一样生活在地下
He lives underground, like a rat.
他见不到太阳  不能去上学
He never sees the sun, he'll never go to school.
我能给他提供一个家庭
I'm offering him a family.
你时不时还能看看他
You can see him from time to time.
我知道怎么藏我的儿子
I know how to hide my son.
怎么喂饱他  怎么照顾他
To feed and take care of him.
我一直跟你说  你的孩子生下来就死了
I keep telling you, your son was born dead.
从没存在过
He doesn't exist.
哪怕一瓶番茄酱也有个名字
Even a bottle of ketchup has a name.
还有生产日期和保质期
With date of manufacture and expiry.
我不想听这些
I can't listen to this!
你还缺多少钱
How much are you short?
-500美元  -还少500美元吗
- $500. - You're short $500?
我500美元都能买个孩子了
I can buy a kid for $500.
只要你别说我阿斯普罗是个骗子
So you don't think that Aspro is a crook,
我就再给你降200美元
I'll go lower by $200,
给你宽限7天
and give you 7 more days.
下次来  要么带着钱  要么带着人
Either return with the money, or with your son,
不然干脆别来了
or don't show your pretty face here again.
明白了吗
You understand?
给你时间  要多少给多少
So take your time, all the time you need.
看
Look.
你好啊  过得怎么样  朋友
Hello, how are you, friend?
挺好的  兄弟
Doing well, my brother?
我看见你在卷烟
I saw you rolling a joint.
我吗
Me?
你妈是个肥婊子
Your mother is a fat whore...
你个娘娘腔窝囊废
You pussy looking wimp.
你个狗杂种
You cocksucker.
别再招摇撞骗了蠢货
Stop fooling around shithead.
混蛋
Asshole!
你妈是个卖国贼
Your mother wears army boots.
把你该死的窗户关上  你们的食物闻起来恶心死了
Close your damn window I'm sick of smelling your food!
她要是再烦  我就让她吃屎
I'll make her eat shit if she keeps nagging me.
要不我拉在她脸上吧
Do I lay into her, or what?
什么个肥婊子
What a fat whore...
贱人
Dirty bitch...
你想要
Are you going to...?
我受够了  你要帮我把工资要回来
I've had enough, you need to get my pay!
你知道那家伙  你帮我找的工作
You know the guy. You found the job for me.
我不是老板  我没法给你钱
I'm not the owner. I can't give you money.
我要是能给就给你了
If it was up to me, I'd give it to you.
我是泰吉斯  你认识我吗
I am Tigest, you know me?
认出来了吗
Recognize me?
明天下午再来  可能老板会在
Come back after noon, maybe the boss will be here.
不  不能预付  这才月初呢
No. No advances. It's early in the month.
你是非法的  我已经在够冒险了
You're illegal, I'm already taking risks.
求你了  让我做什么都行
Please, I'll do what you want.
这是老板娘的身份证
Here's the boss lady's I.D. card.
我为你偷的  你知道她很信任我
I stole it for you. You know how much she trusts me.
这不是坏事  是为了孩子
It's not a bad thing, it's for the kid
你知道如果他们发现了会怎样吗
You know what happens if they find out?
他们会把你和孩子一起驱逐出境
They'll expel you with the kid.
天知道我们会是个什么下场
God knows what they'll do to me.
我只是个看门的
I'm just a watchman.
他们一眨眼就会把我换掉
They'll replace me in the blink of an eye.
-你连照片都不想看吗  -不想
- You don't want to see a photo? - I don't.
求你了  走吧
Please, just go.
我之前为一位女士工作
Before, I worked for a lady.
后来  我跑了
Then, I ran away.
所以她必须假装是我原来的老板
So she has to pretend she's my old boss.
就说  不需要我了
And say I'm no longer needed.
她不想要你了
She doesn't want you.
所以她把我转给了你
So she'll transfer me to you.
你当我的赞助者
You'll become my sponsor.
我的老板
My boss.
这是杰奎琳
This is Jacqueline.
我是谁
Who am I?
我可不是杰奎琳  我是达德
I'm not Jaqueline, I'm Daad.
我会假装是杰奎琳
I will pretend I'm Jacqueline.
你替我工作
You have to work for me?
但我不需要员工了
But I don't need an employee.
天呐  我要跳楼了
Oh God, I'm jumping out the window.
我雇不起女仆
I can't pay for a maid.
我没有500美元来雇她
I don't have $500 to hire her.
你看这只蟑螂
You see this cockroach?
它都明白了
It already understood.
我要是问它  它都能把整个骗局说清楚
If I ask it, it will explain the whole scam.
和所有黎巴嫩人一样
As with all Lebanese...
放弃老家  搬去新家
To relinquish and transfer.
你住在哪里
Where do you live?
阿拉克斯
Arax.
公寓吗
Apartment?
卡其克派
Khachik Papikian.
哈鲁特先生  有打火机吗
Do you have a light, Mr. Harout?
谢谢
Thank you.
不好意思  你抽烟吗
Sorry, do you smoke?
不了  谢谢
No, thank you.
你为什么不想要这个女孩了
Why don't you want this girl?
我孩子们在加拿大  上帝保佑他们
I have children in Canada, God bless them.
他们想给我请个菲佣
They want to send me a Filipina.
他们现在怎么样了
Are they better?
-名声变好了  -真是不一样了
- More prestigious. - They're different.
那你呢  你也同意为这个男人工作吗
And you? Do you accept to work for this man?
我想尽可能的
I want to sponsor this Filipina.
帮到这个菲律宾姑娘
With everything.
我想帮忙
I want to help her.
她是埃塞俄比亚人
She's Ethiopian.
我想让她服侍我的老婆
I want to give her to my wife.
你是干什么的
What is your occupation?
我有个电器行
I have an electronics store.
叫什么名字
What is it called?
哈鲁奇姆
Haroutchum...
电器
Electric.
这个女孩住在哪
The address where the girl will reside?
布哈莫的达乌哈
Dawra, Bourj Hamoud.
你的电话号码是
Your telephone number?
09...
456什么的
4, 5, 6... Something like that.
什么叫  什么的
Something like that?
这个男的是亚美尼亚的
This man is Armenian.
别信他的鬼话
You can't take him literally.
快把你电话号码给我  09然后
Give me your right number, 09...?
-34  -34
- 3, 4... - 3, 4...
-56  -56
- 5, 6... - 5, 6...
然后是7吧
Then 7?
耍我们一通然后给我们喝咖啡
He screws us over, then offers us coffee?
真是谢谢他全家  不喝
No thanks, we don't want your coffee.
他没报警就谢天谢地了
Thank God he didn't call the cops.
让他报  随便报
Let him call police!
没错  我就是大麻之王
Yes, I'm the King of Hashish...
这是什么
What is it?
我有好看一点吗
Do I look different?
你去哪
Where are you going?
给我妈妈打个电话
To call my mother.
然后去艾哈德露天集市拿点东西
Then Souk El Ahad to pick up a few things.
别担心  赞恩会在这陪你
You're not alone, Zain is here.
过会儿见
See you later.
拜呀  赞恩
Goodbye, Zain.
拜拜
Bye.
这个月我不能给你寄钱了
I can't send any money this month.
因为我最近在学英语
I'm taking English classes.
我很抱歉  妈妈
I'm sorry, mother.
我老板的夫人对我很好
My boss lady is good to me.
我没脸向她开口要钱
I'm ashamed to ask her for money.
我爱你  妈妈
I love you, mom.
拉希尔
Rahil?
去马那哈吗
Manara?
去  上车吧
Yes, hop in.
昨天开始就没见到她
I haven't seen her since yesterday.
我以为她生病了
I thought she was sick.
她去艾哈德集市  但是一直没回来
She was going to the souk but never came home.
可能她去找阿斯普罗了吧
Maybe she went to Aspro's.
阿斯普罗  他是谁
Aspro? Who is Aspro?
他在集市上有个摊子
He has a stand at Souk Al Ahad.
上衣只要两千块
Pullovers for only 2000!
先生  请问阿斯普罗的摊位在哪
Sir, where is Aspro's stand?
阿斯普罗的吗  往那走
Aspro? Over that way.
就是那个阿斯普罗吗
The real Aspro?
找拉希尔吗
Rahil?
你怎么知道拉希尔
How do you know Rahil?
-我是她的亲戚  -亲戚
- We're related. - Related?
怎么个亲戚
Show me.
看不出来吗
It's obvious.
她爸那的亲戚还是她妈那的
Paternally or maternally?
这是她的儿子约纳斯吗
This is her son Yonas?
没错吧
Isn't it?
为什么约纳斯跟你在一起
Why is Yonas with you?
拉希尔昨晚离开了
Rahil left last night.
到现在还没回来
She hasn't returned.
把约纳斯给我
Give me Yonas.
-不行  不给  -怎么  你怕什么
- No, no... - Why, are you afraid?
我的小约纳斯  我可对他了如指掌
He's my little Yonas! I'm all for him.
他跟他妈妈一个样  都是个小骗子
He's a little scammer, just like his mother.
亚西尔  给这边俩兔崽子炸两个丸子
Yasser, 2 falafels for these two rabbits!
你吃吗
You want to eat?
你没给她打电话吗
You haven't phoned her?
我没手机
I don't have a phone.
她关机了
Her cellphone is off.
谢了  亚西尔
Thanks, Yasser.
-进来吃吧  -不了  谢谢你
- Come eat inside. - No, thank you.
她要是来了我怎么跟她说
What do I say if she comes?
就说我们在家等她
Say we're waiting at home.
-在这呆着吧  -不  不了
- Stay here. - No, no.
在这等着吧  万一她来了呢
Wait here in case she passes by.
打扰一下
Excuse me?
这要从哪打开
Where can I open this?
帮我拿着
Hold this for me.
-给  -谢谢你
- There. - Thanks.
不客气
No problem.
-你饿吗  -不饿
- Are you hungry? - No.
你叫什么
What's your name?
易卜拉欣
Ibrahim.
-那他呢  -他叫
- What about him? - He's called...
叫阿萨德
Assaad.
-你呢  -梅苏
- And you? - Maysoun.
这小孩是你偷来的吗  想让他乞讨赚钱的吗
You stole him? Or are you using him to beg for money?
他是我弟弟
He's my brother.
你俩看起来一点都不像
You don't look alike.
我小时候跟他一样黑
We're all born black like him.
然后
And then...
时间一久  就白了
with time, we get lighter.
这些盒子能值多少钱
How much are these boxes?
那得看谁开车
It depends on the car.
要是一个女的开过去
If a woman drives by...
如果她手上戴着戒指
Look at her hand, if she's wearing a ring...
那就说  上帝保佑你
You say, "God protect you..."
并且留住你的丈夫
"and keep your husband."
如果她没戴戒指
If she has no ring,
就说  愿上帝赐你一个丈夫
you say, "God send you a husband!"
别再舔手啦  脏死了
Stop licking your hands, they're much too dirty.
在那排队  埃塞俄比亚人
Line-up over there, Ethiopians...
你怀了吗
Are you pregnant?
别告诉他们
You can't tell them.
他们会抢走你的孩子
They'll take him from you.
约纳斯  我的孩子啊  原谅我
Yonas, my son, forgive me!
看在慈爱的上帝的份上  宽恕我
For the love of God forgive me!
有什么婴儿用品吗
Do you have something for a baby?
有
Yes.
多少钱
How much?
250块的还是1000块的
For 250 or one at 1000.
250的
I'll take the 250.
尝尝
Taste.
就尝一口
Just this once.
说真的
No kidding...
这个是不是比卷饼还好吃
Isn't this better than shawarma?
别整个吞下去  会得病的
Don't swallow it whole, you'll get sick!
你吞下去了吗
You swallowed it?
好吃吗
Is it good?
慢慢吃  大家伙
Enjoy it, big guy.
没水吗
No water?
这个狗日的烂国家
Fuck this shitty country!
她都不打听打听自己的儿子吗
She doesn't ask about her son?
都不回来看看吗
Doesn't look in on him?
你妈比我的还烂
Your mother is worse than mine.
你先进  约纳斯先生
After you, Mister Yonas.
进吧
Go ahead.
易卜拉欣
Ibrahim!
你在干嘛
What are you doing there?
我在卖这些锅
I'm selling these pots.
这些锅都破了
Those crappy pots?
比你背的蠢花圈好
Better than that stupid wreath you're carrying!
这是葬礼用的  蠢货
That's for the cemetery, idiot.
很容易就能卖掉
I could sell it easily.
会全都卖光的
They'll buy it all.
想打赌吗
You want to bet?
赌一顿饭
Let's bet a plate of food.
我要肉丸子和希什公园  你呢
I want meat rolls with Chich Barak. You?
希什公园为一种黎巴嫩特色菜  是在酸奶酱中熬煮的肉馅饺子  常辅以干薄荷和蒜  以当地一处公园命名
我死也要吃到希什公园  又辣
I'd die for some Chich Barak, hot...
天啊
My God...
不能随便一顿  得赌一顿多的
Not just any plate, an enormous one...
你从哪领救济的食物
Where does your food relief come from?
你上次说到了
You talked about it last time.
啊  你是说卫生院吧
Ah, you mean the dispensary?
我能和你一起去吗
Can I go with you?
那可不行  你是黎巴嫩的  我是叙利亚的
No, you're Lebanese, I'm Syrian.
你从哪找到的那个小兔崽子
Where did you find that rabbit?
管好你自己吧
Mind your own business.
老肥猪  我们走
You old goat. Let's go.
你不能让开吗
Could you move away?
-还是想拳头打在脸上才舒服吗  -行了  易卜拉欣  走吧
- Or you want to taste my fist? - Come, Ibrahim. Let's go.
反正我马上就要走了  离开这个国家
Anyhow, I'm leaving this country, I'm outta here.
去哪
Where to?
我会把我的生意什么的都留给你
I'll leave you the business and everything.
都是你的了
It's all yours.
你要去哪
Where are you going?
去瑞士
To Sweden.
那里有一个全是叙利亚人的社区
There's a neighborhood full of Syrians there.
没人关心你从哪来
Nobody asks where you're from.
也没有纷争  什么都没有
No hassles, nothing.
我还会有自己的房间
I'll have my own room.
不敲门不准进的那种  我想让谁进才能进
Nobody enters without knocking. I decide who comes in.
那的小孩不会莫名其妙地死掉
Kids there die from natural causes.
我想和你一起走
I want to go with you.
行啊  但是你得有钱
Sure, but you need money.
要多少
How much?
三百左右吧  不多
Around $300. Not much.
三百很多了
$300 is a lot
你知道一个人叫奥什么
You know Os...
奥斯帕吗
Ospar?
阿斯普罗吗
Aspro?
就是他  在集市里
Yes, in the souk.
他怎么了
What about him?
这是他报的价
This is his number.
他安排的旅行  他给了我这张纸
He sets up the trip. He gave me this paper.
我在他的报价边上画了条船
I drew a boat beside his number.
挂着彩灯的大船
A boat with pretty lights,
船上还有吃的
and great food.
阿萨德能一起去吗
Could Assaad come too?
他会游泳吗
Does he know how to swim?
我能帮他
I'll help him.
我不知道  这得去问奥斯普罗
I don't know. We have to ask Ospro.
是阿斯普罗  不是奥斯普罗
Aspro, not Ospro.
阿斯普罗
Aspro.
你从哪来
Where are you from?
我吗  叙利亚来的
Me? Syria.
叙利亚的哪
Where in Syria?
阿勒颇
Alep.
这是你的弟弟吗  是的  弟弟
This is your brother? Yes, my brother.
我是说  这是我弟弟
I mean, this is my brother.
他叫什么
What's his name?
诺瓦斯
Nawras.
我们两天没吃东西了
We haven't eaten for 2 days.
他为什么这么黑
Why is he so black?
我妈在怀她的时候喝了好多咖啡
My mother drank a lot of coffee when she was pregnant.
一天喝一壶
A whole coffeepot each day.
你的证件在哪
Where is your card?
我在河边散步时丢了
I lost it walking near a river.
你在河边散步吗
You walked beside a river?
是的  我的东西都掉到河里去了
Yes, and my papers fell in the water.
我拿不回来
I couldn't catch them.
你是怎么到这来的
How did you get here?
我们在叙利亚的家里  我觉得应该是
We were at home in Syria, and our neighbor...
我们的邻居告发的我们
He denounced us, I think.
我不确定
I'm not certain...
但我怀疑是他
But I suspect him.
大炮打中了我们的房子
A shell fell on our house.
然后我们就跟兰博一样四处为家
We started moving like Rambo.
兰博为史泰龙于1982年主演的动作片《第一滴血》的主角  是一名勇猛善战的退伍越战军人
兰博就是四处为家
Rambo, who keeps moving.
你四处为家
You started moving?
是的  就跟他在战壕里一样
Yes, like him, in the trenches.
那么你想要什么
So what do you want?
你给什么我要什么  牛奶  尿布什么的最好
Whatever you can give. Milk and diapers, mostly.
牛奶和尿布
Milk and diapers.
或许再来点拉面和醋味薯片更好
Maybe some ramen and some vinegar chips.
站起来
Stand up.
好一辆豪车  过来  把你的宝马开过来让我瞧瞧
What a Lamborghini! Come here, let me see that.
拉希尔还没回来吗
Rahil hasn't come back?
没
No...
我是说  怎么了  拉希尔吗
I mean, yes! Rahil?
她前不久刚回来
She came back a while ago!
是嘛
For sure...
你拉的这什么玩意儿
What are you dragging behind you?
原子弹吗  还是火箭
A nuclear bomb, or a rocket?
新型储水罐
A brand new water tank.
这个新型储水罐值多少钱
How much for that "brand new" water tank?
-两万  -两万块呢
- 20000. - 20000?
亚西尔
Yasser!
别两万了  给他三万吧
Give the kid 30000 instead of 20.
约纳斯哟
Yonas...
怎么瘦成这样了
Why is Yonas so thin?
没吃东西吗
You're not eating?
他看着不太健康
He looks sick.
天啊  你比狗还臭
My God you smell like dogs!
我跟拉希尔说过了
I already spoke to Rahil.
我跟她说了一户人家会接管约纳斯
I told her a family would take care of Yonas.
他们会照顾他  给他买衣服什么的
They'll care for him, buy him clothing...
然后你可以拿到500块
And you can put $500 in your pockets.
不错吧
Sound good?
你怎么说
So?
听说你能帮人偷渡去土耳其
They say you help people travel to Turkey?
你想偷渡吗
You want to travel?
我想
I'd like to.
你想去哪
Where do you want to go?
去土耳其
Turkey.
我是说瑞典
I mean Sweden.
-瑞典土耳其  你想去哪都行  -哪个好一点
- Sweden, Turkey, wherever you like. - Which is nicer?
你随便挑  月球我也能给你搞上去
You choose, I can get you to the moon.
只要说服拉希尔交出孩子
Just convince Rahil about this boy.
明白吗  小伙子
Alright, kid?
给  老板
Here, boss.
拿着这个  跟拉希尔说阿斯普罗打过招呼了
Take this and tell Rahil that Aspro says hello.
清楚吗
Alright?
我会问她的
I'll ask Rahil.
可别忘了
You do that.
约纳斯  给我个衣服夹子
Yonas, give me a clothespin.
这么做可以让手暖和点
Do like this to warm your hands.
我的小妹妹自己洗裤子  因为我们妈妈病了
My little sister washed her pants because our mother was sick.
她把处方跟衣服一起洗了吗
She washed the prescription with the clothing?
我给你一板
I'll give you one card...
你补上少的三千块我再给你剩下的
You get the rest when you pay the missing 3000.
就一板啊  给我两板吧
One card? Give me two.
停下
No.
离远点
Stay back!
我看见你往这儿走了  我还没瞎
I see you moving forward. I'm not blind.
伙计们  能过来帮帮我吗
Guys, can you come help me?
想来一口曲马多吗
Gulps of Tramadol, are you into that?
一口一千块
One gulp for 1000.
帮我搬一下这个
Help me carry all this.
来帮帮我
Come help me!
我会给你个好价钱的  兄弟
I'll give you a good price, brother.
快来  赶紧的
Come on, hurry!
伙计们  他有曲马多
Guys, he has Tramadol!
-我的曲马多按口算  -你能弄到伟哥什么的吗
- Tramadol by the gulp. - Can you get Viagra or Simo?
-你有嗨粉吗  -小可爱  真是曲马多吗
- Do you have Rivo? - Farawla, Tradamol?
-吸入的吗  -我卖的是口服的
Freebase? I'm in the juice business.
这是嗨粉  不过是饮用的
This is Rivo, but in juice form.
小鬼  你这卖的不是海水吗
Are you selling us sea water little man?
海水劲最大了
Nothing better than sea water!
我有口服的曲马多  要吗
I have Tramadol by the gulp. Interested?
一千块一剂
1000 for a swig.
过来  选一个你想去的国家
Go on, choose your dream country.
我们去瑞典吧  那儿更好
Let's go to Sweden, it's nicer.
跟梅苏那个傻子一起去
We'll go with that fool Maysoun.
在瑞典
In Sweden,
不会有人来烦你
nobody ever bothers you.
从阳台上撒尿也没人管
You can even piss from the balcony, and nobody says a thing!
把你欠的钱还了  畜生
Pay what you owe him, bitch!
带着你的小萝卜头滚蛋
Take your doll and get out!
马上就走  夯货
I'm going, asshole!
去把你的屁股剁吧剁吧吃了吧
Go heat up your ass, when it's well-cooked, eat it!
别碰小孩  王八蛋
Don't touch the kid, shithead.
滚
Get out!
走开
Bugger off!
滚
Get out!
再砸门要烂了  你干什么
You'll break the door! What are you doing?
哪个龟孙子换了锁还把我东西都扔出来了
Who's the son of a whore that changed the lock and threw my things out?
你东西不在这儿吗  你谁啊
Your things are right there. Who are you?
里面还有
I have things inside.
你的东西在房主那
Your things are at the owners.
房主那猪脑子在哪
Where is this stupid owner?
叫你那烂货朋友来
Go find your slutty friend.
不然我就叫房主了
Or else I'll call the owner.
好啊  顺便替我亲他一下
Give him a big kiss for me!
那贱人是你什么人
How do you know that slut?
我是她弟弟
I'm her brother.
哪个下水道钻出来的弟弟
What shithole did you come from?
你再不走小心我不客气
Bug off before I go crazy!
我要报警了
I'm calling the cops!
等着瞧
You'll see!
我要是不砸门  傻逼房主出来吗
If I don't break the door, where is that dumb owner?
滚  不然别想活着走过去
Get away or I'll break you in two!
闭嘴  闭嘴  滚
Shut up! Shut up! Go away!
把  钱  还  给  老  子
I. Want. My. Fucking. Money!
呆这别动
Stay here. Don't move.
回那去
Go over there!
快去
Go.
回去
Go back!
那儿
Go over there!
是的  兄弟
Yes, my friend.
听着
Listen...
我要送个小孩过去
I'm sending you a small kid.
现在看着跟狗似的  给他拾掇得像人点
He looks like a dog now, make him look human.
怎么  我得带他过去吗
OK? I have to bring him?
好的
Alright.
干嘛耷拉着脸
Why are you sad?
没事
It's nothing.
这是好事  我们谈过了
It's a good thing. We agreed.
你有证件吗
You have papers?
身份证
Identity card?
不知道  在家吧  可能
Don't know. At the house, maybe.
我得证明你是个真人
I need proof you exist.
身份证  政府文件
An identity card, government papers,
报纸上的照片
a newspaper photograph...
这样才能从贝鲁特出港口
So I can get you out by the port in Beirut.
明白了吗
Understand?
不要担心约纳斯
Don't worry about Yonas.
我爱他  会给他找个好归宿的
I love him, he'll go to a good family.
带你去的人会照顾你
The people you'll travel with will take good care of you.
记得我那个叫亚西尔的手下吗  去找他
Remember Yasser who works for me? Go see him...
他会带你去剃头
He'll send you for a haircut.
然后回家  带什么东西过来
Then go home and bring...what?
-证件  -证件
- Papers.  - Papers.
清楚了吗
Alright?
一百  两百  三百  四百
Here's one, two, three, four...
钱给你
Here.
你不是说五百吗
You promised $500.
你当吃喝不要钱吗
You want to eat and drink for free?
那一百块算饭钱
$100 for your food
亲一个
Kiss me.
照顾好自己
Take care now, go on.
没事了  你可以走了
It's alright, you can go
我说了我会照顾他
I said I'd take care of him.
赞恩
Zain!
你在这呆多久了
How long have you been here?
不关你的事
None of your business.
你去哪浪了
Where have you been?
去哪了
哪儿  哪儿  哪儿
Where? Where? Where?
天杀的
I curse you!
反正我也不是回来看你的
Anyhow, I didn't come to see you,
也不是沙发上那臭毛鼠
nor for that asshole over there.
我要我的证件
I want my papers.
哦  是吗  宝贝儿子
Yes, of course my dear!
塞利姆  快来听笑话
Selim, want to hear a good one?
你儿子要他的证件
Your son wants his papers!
我的证件呢
Where are my papers?
这么长时间你跑哪去了
Where were you all this time?
不关你事
None of your business.
不关我的事
Not my business?
你要证件干什么
Why do you want your papers?
要去捡垃圾吗
Found work as a garbageman?
我的证件  身份证  什么都行
My papers, my identity card, whatever!
也不想想谁鸟你  谁鸟我们家
Nobody cares about you or us.
别跟我这摔东西
Don't play tough with me!
你看着  这里是证件
You'll see, I'll give you your papers.
我证件多了去了  随你选
I have all kinds of papers. Just choose any.
有那种能关我一辈子的证件
I have papers that would jail me for life.
开除通知
Expulsion notice.
这张  这张最厉害
This one. The most important.
来看看这张
Come. Look at this paper!
付不起的医院账单
A hospital bill that breaks my heart.
亲爱的儿子  家里就剩四面墙了
We're less than nothing, my son.
白吃白喝的废物
Parasites.
人没证件也能活
Just live without papers...
再废话我就把你从窗子口扔出去完事
Or I'll toss you from the window, and end it all.
听清楚了吗
You understand?
滚  不然我撕烂你那张脸
Get out or I'll break your face.
让他走  塞利姆
Let him go, Selim!
告诉那个让你来的人  我没给你办过证
Tell whoever sent you I never got you papers!
从哪来滚回哪去
Go back where you came from!
怎么就生了这么个遭天谴的废物
I curse you and the day you were born!
谁住院了
Who's in the hospital?
闭嘴  塞利姆  别说了
Not a word Selim, don't say any more!
谁进医院了
Who went to the hospital?
谁住院了
Who's in the hospital?
让他滚  不然剁了他
Make him leave or I'll kill him!
-垃圾  -谁进医院了
- Piece of garbage! - Who was in the hospital?
-麻烦精  -谁住院了
- Troublemaker! - Who went to the hospital?
说话啊
Talk to me.
谁住院了
Who was in the hospital?
那个婊子养的干了什么
What did he do, that son of a whore?
他对我妹妹干了什么
What did he do to her?
他干了什么
What did he do?
萨哈尔死了
Sahar is gone. It's over.
她死了
She's gone?
我给你看看死了是什么意思
You'll see what going means.
我告诉你死了是什么意思
I'll show you what it means.
-回来  兔崽子  -他拿着刀
- Come back, little shit! - He has a knife!
回来  不然老子打烂你的脸
Come back, or I'll smash your face!
回来  王八犊子
Come back you dog!
老子两只手就能弄死你
With my bare hands!
把手铐摘了
Take his handcuffs off.
你是那个谁的丈夫
You're the husband of...
-萨哈尔  -对  萨哈尔
- Sahar. - Sahar.
她嫁给你时多大
How old was she when you married?
-11岁  -11岁吗
- 11. - 11 years old?
11岁就可以结婚了吗
Is an 11 year old of age to marry?
她知道结婚什么意思吗
She knows what marriage means?
我觉得
From what I know...
她知道
Yes, she can.
我是说  她已经成熟了
I mean she had ripened.
是吗
Really?
原来她跟水果蔬菜一样还会熟啊
Didn't know she was a tomato or potato to become ripe!
赞恩  冷静
Zain, calm down!
我不知道她会因为这个死
I didn't know she could die from it.
好多小姑娘都是这个年纪结婚的
Many girls here marry at that age.
我后妈就是
Even my step-mother married at that age.
她现在还活着  就在这
She's here, still alive.
她什么时候怀孕的
When did she get pregnant?
婚后两三个月
2 or 3 months after.
没出什么问题吗
Everything was normal?
一开始我没发现有什么不对劲
At first, I didn't notice anything wrong.
后来她开始出血
Then she started to bleed.
大出血
She bled a lot.
然后呢
What happened next?
他们带她跟她爹妈去了医院
They brought her to hospital with her parents.
还没进去她就死了
She died at the entrance.
医院不让她进去
We couldn't get her admitted.
为什么不让她进去
Why did they refuse to admit her?
她没有证件
Because she has no papers.
够了  她快被你问崩溃了
That's enough, you're besieging her with questions.
我一辈子都过得像个孙子  你还质疑我
I've been a slave all my life and you dare question me?
你居然挑我的刺  你过过我的日子吗
How dare you judge me? Have you walked in my shoes?
你吃过我吃的苦吗
Have you lived what I've lived?
没有  你根本不需要受那些苦
No, never, you'll never have to go through it!
你连做梦都想象不到
Not even in your worst nightmares.
如果你是我  你没准早就上吊了
In my place, you would have hung yourself!
想想  家里什么都没有
Imagine feeding your kids sugar water,
孩子只能喝糖水
because you have nothing else.
要是杀人放火能让孩子们活下去  我早就干了
I'd commit 100 crimes to keep my children alive!
他们都是我的孩子
They're my children.
轮不到别人指责我
Nobody has a right to judge me. I am my own judge.
那是我的身上掉下来的肉
The flesh of my flesh!
听到了吗
Do you hear me?
叙利亚人  侯赛因
The Syrian, Hussein...
埃及人  穆罕默德
The Egyptian, Mohammad...
能听我们说句话吗
Could we have your attention?
我们跟牧师一起来的  来了解你们
We're here with the priest, to get to know you.
陪你们呆一阵
To have some good times with you.
帮你们振作起来
To help pick up your spirits.
大家唱歌吧
Let's sing a song.
赞恩·哈吉  带着你的东西去办公室报到
Zain Al Hajj, get your things and report to the office.
赞恩
Zain?
Zain!
你怎么在这里
What are you doing here?
约纳斯呢
Zain, where is Yonas?
赞恩
Zain!
赞恩  约纳斯呢
Zain, where is Yonas ?
赞恩
Zain!
我儿子呢
Where is my son?
约纳斯在哪
Where is Yonas? Where?
你把他给谁了
Who did you leave him with?
我儿子一个人
My son is alone!
他的眼睛
His eye...
这边的
on this side,
是蓝色的
is blue, blue, blue.
他两只眼睛都是蓝色的
Both his eyes are blue ?
不  有一只是棕色的
No. One eye is brown.
另一只是蓝色的
And one is blue.
你住在自由之地
You are live on Freedom Forever.
麻烦把电视音量调低点
Please lower the volume on your television set.
我看你的节目很久了
I've watched your show for a while now...
我知道你总是关注社会问题
I know you always tackle social problems...
你怎么样
How are you?
生病了吗  感冒了吗
Are you sick? Did you catch cold?
恭喜啊  亲戚已经不再吊唁了吗
Congratulations, your mourning is over?
不用披麻戴孝了吗
No longer wearing black?
我给你带了点糖
I brought you candy to munch on.
吃吧  赞恩
Eat them, Zain.
你怎么这么恨我
Why do you hate me so much?
我也没有办法  我什么都做不了
I'm powerless. I couldn't do anything.
她是我闺女  我也心疼
She was my daughter, it's my pain.
你来干什么
Why are you here?
上帝带走一样东西
When God takes something,
就会用另一样补偿你
He offers something in return.
他用什么补偿你了
What did he offer you?
我怀孕了
I'm pregnant.
你会再有个弟弟或者妹妹
You'll have a brother or sister.
真恶心
I feel sick.
我希望是个闺女  我们会叫她扎哈尔
I hope it's a girl. We'll name her Zahar.
听听你说的是人话吗
Your words pierce my heart.
等你出来  她已经能走会跑了
When you get out, she'll be walking, and playing...
我不想再见你了
I no longer want to see you.
你没有心
You're heartless.
放开  我要走
Leave me alone, I want to leave.
我爸死了之后  我就没笑过了
Since my father died I haven't smiled...
这份关于儿童不公的报告
This report on injustices against children
深深地触动了我们的观众
has deeply touched our audience.
如果您有什么意见或建议
If you'd like to comment on what you've just watched...
请拨打09658856
09658856.
赞恩  你旁边有大人吗
Is there an adult next to you, Zain ?
有个警察
An officer.
警察
An officer?
赞恩  你从哪里打的电话
Where are you calling from, Zain?
监狱
From prison.
我听到赞恩的声音了
I hear Zain's voice.
监狱
From prison?
哪个监狱
Which prison?
是他
It's him!
鲁米耶未成年监狱
Roumieh Prison for Minors.
赞恩  你为什么打电话  我能做什么
Zain, why are you calling? What can I do for you?
我想说我父母对我的不好
I want to make a complaint against my parents.
嗨  兄弟们
Hey boys!
赞恩上电视了
Zain is on television!
赞恩  这里在直播  你想说什么
Zain, you're on live. What would you like to say?
我希望大人们能听我说
I'd want adults to listen to me.
我希望养不起孩子的大人不要生孩子
I want adults who can't raise kids not to have any.
关于童年  我日后能记住的只有
What will I remember?
暴力  辱骂  殴打
Violence, insults or beatings,
链子  水管  皮带打在身上的感觉
hit with chains, pipes, or a belt?
他们说过最好听的话是  兔崽子滚出去
The kindest words I heard were "get out son of a whore!"
让开  废物
"Bug off, piece of garbage!"
生活根本就全是虱子
Life is a pile of shit.
破鞋都比它华美
Not worth more than my shoe.
我活在地狱里
I live in hell here.
不过是生活里煎熬的一块烂肉
I burn like rotting meat.
你怎么样
How are you?
生活是个千人骑万人乘的泼货
Life is a bitch.
我以为我们会成为好人
I thought we'd become good people,
被人爱戴
loved by all.
可上帝根本不希望我们能被人爱
But God doesn't want that for us.
他希望我们是别人家的脏抹布
He'd rather we be washrags for others.
你现在怀着的孩子也会变成我这样
The child you're carrying will be like I am.
赞恩  你希望你父母怎么做
Zain, what do you want from you parents?
我希望他们不要再生了
I want them to stop having kids.
大点声
Louder.
我希望他们不要再生了
I want them to stop having kids.
你希望他们不要再生了
You want them to stop having kids.
是的
Yes.
我觉得他们不会再生了
I don't think they'll have more kids.
她肚子里那个呢
And the one in her tummy?
还会生出来对吧
It will be born, no?
我们发现了一个仓库  里面有十五人
We've discovered a depot where 15 people were sequestered...
站在线上
Toes on the line.
往右一点
A little to the right.
不不  往左
No, the left.
我说的是你的右边
I mean your right.
可这边是我的右边
But this is my right.
这边是我的左边
And this is my left.
下巴抬高
Lift your chin.
往前看
Look straight ahead.
笑一笑
Smile.
笑一笑  赞恩
Smile, Zain.
这是拍护照  不是拍遗照
It's a passport photo, not a death certificate!
英文字幕以ECLAIR提供的法文字幕与时间轴为基础翻译
Based on the French subtitles and timings by ECLAIR